A Guide to the Papers of Hugh Scott, 1944-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Hugh Scott 1944-1981
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10,200-f, -g, -h, -i, -j, -k, -l, -m, -o
This collection consists of ca. 8,700 items (20 Hollinger boxes, ca. 7.5 linear shelf feet.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The additions to the Hugh Scott Papers were a gift of the Honorable Hugh Scott of Washington, D.C., and include 10,200-f (the larger portion of papers) received December 12, 1980, and other additions: 10,200- g (April 13, 1981); 10,200-h (April 14, 1981); 10,200-i (May 22, 1981); 10,200-j (July 29, 1981); 10,200-k (January 5, 1982); 10,200-l (January 5, 1982); 10,200-m (January 12, 1982); and 10,200-o (May 11, 1982).
Scope and Content Information
This material added to the Hugh Scott Papers consists of ca. 8,700 items (20 Hollinger boxes, ca. 7.5 linear shelf feet), 1944-1981, of personal correspondence and papers, political papers, photographs, printed material and memorabilia primarily pertaining to Scott's last five years as a United States senator. These additions also include some material from his legal career, and from his position as a distinguished public figure following his retirement from the Senate in 1977.
Topics of interest in the correspondence, 1976-1978, include oriental art, Scott's affiliation with Randolph-Macon College and the University of Virginia, his visits abroad, and his retirement. Correspondence with notable members of the Senate and House of Representatives is included, as is some with family; there is also some legal correspondence. A "VIP correspondence" file, chiefly 1961-1968, includes letters signed by Richard M. Nixon, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Dean Rusk, Hubert H. Humphrey, Carl Hayden, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Jr., and Levertt Saltonstall.
The personal papers, 1971-1981, relate to such topics as the Board of Foreign Scholarships, the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, the Commission on Critical Choices for Americans, Oxford University lectures by Scott, Randolph-Macon College, and Youth for Understanding.
The political papers, 1958-1980, include material for Scott's 1964 campaign for the U.S. Senate, the Panama Canal treaties, his books regarding China and The Life of the Party, and his trips to other foreign countries. Scott visited Australia in 1978, Canada in 1975, China in 1973 and 1978, England in 1977, Japan in 1974, 1976, 1978, and 1980; Malaysia and the Far East in 1976, South East Asia in 1972, and the U.S.S.R. in 1975.
The photographs, 1953 and 1969-1981, are chiefly from Scott's visits abroad. Photographs of the Youth for Understanding conference in Japan include Senators William Roth, Robert Byrd, Howard Baker, and James William Fulbright, Representative Silvio Conte, Prime Minister Suzuki, and Foreign Minister Ito. Also included are photographs of Scott and Secretary of State John F. Dulles and Attorney General Herbert Brownell at the Inauguration of President Eisenhower; as well as Scott, Jimmy Carter, and Governor William Averell Harriman during discussions of the Panama Canal treaties; and of Oriental art. In addition there is an engraving of Thomas Jefferson by Jacques Couché.
Organization
The papers are organized in the following series: I. Correspondence, II. Personal Papers, III, Political Papers, IV. Photographs, V. Printed Material and Miscellaneous, and VI. Memorabilia. Folders within the series are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- I. Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Personal A-G 1976-1977, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Personal H-R 1976-1977, 7 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Personal S-Z 1976-1977, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Personal A-G 1978, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Personal H-Z 1978, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Personal A-Z 1979, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Robert Barnett re Asia Society 1975 (Box 5)
  - John Bartol 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - Simon Kriger 1959-1962, 1969, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Re: Miles Lilly and possible book on Pennsylvania 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Re: Randolph-Macon College Endowment Campaign, Fundraising 1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: V.I.P. 1942, 1961-1968, n.d. (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Christmas cards, Post cards 1980, n.d. (Box 6)
- II. Personal Papers
  - Asia Society 1966, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Board of Foreign Scholarships 1979, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Board of Regents, Smithsonian Inst. 1976 (Box 6)
  - Board of Visitors, University of Va. 1971, 1975-1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Commission on Critical Choices for Americans; Agenda and Related Material 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Commission on Critical Choices for Americans Agenda and Related Material for second meeting 1974 (Box 8)
  - Hawaii: Aug. 3-Aug. 24, 1975 1975 (Box 8)
  - Metal Bank of America 1969, 1973-1976 (Box 8)
  - Oxford University: Lectures 1-8 1967, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Pennsylvania State University: The Maurice K. Goddard Chair 1977-1978 (Box 8)
  - Philadelphia: "The City of Firsts," a complete history published by the Historical Publication Society 1926 (Box 8)
  - Randolph-Macon College 1978-1980 (Box 8)
  - Randolph-Macon College 1978-1980, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Youth for Understanding 1978, n.d. (Box 9)
  - Youth for Understanding 1979 Jan.-Dec., 1980, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Youth for Understanding 1979-1980, 3 folders (Box 11)
    Board of Trustees
    Meetings; Program
    Advisory Council Meetings
    Miscellaneous material
- III. Political Papers
  - Board of Foreign Scholarships Trip 1977-1978 (Box 11)
  - Australia: Board of Foreign Scholarships Trip 1977-1978 (Box 12)
  - Campaign Finances for the Republican National and Pennsylvania State Committees 1958-1964 (Box 12)
  - Campaign Finances for the Scott for State Committee 1964 (Box 12)
  - Campaign Finances and other Related Material for the Win with Scott Committee 1961-1964, n.d. 1961-1965, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - China book material 1972 (Box 12)
  - China: Legal Aspects of International Trade n.d. (Box 12)
  - China Trip: The National Council for U.S.-China Trade 1973 (Box 13)
  - Chinese Normalization: U.S. Political Implications 1976-1977 (Box 13)
  - Contributions to Senate Campaigns 1968 (Box 13)
  - England: London Trip 1976-1977, n.d. (Box 13)
  - Far East n.d. (Box 13)
  - Federal Election Commission 1977 (Box 13)
  - Invitations/Regrets 1978 Oct.-1980 Mar., n.d., 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Israel Trip 1973-1974 (Box 14)
  - "Jades": An article by Hugh Scott 1977 (Box 14)
  - Japan: Tokyo Trip 1974-1975, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Japan Trip 1976-1977, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Japan Trip re Japan-U.S. Businessman's Conference 1977, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Japan/China Trip 1978, 2 folders (Box 15)
  - Japan-U.S. Businessman's Conference 1980 (Box 15)
  - Korea University 1974-1976 (Box 15)
  - The Life of the Party Chapters I-XII 1966, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Malaysia and Far East-Williamsburg VI Conference 1976, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Morocco [1978-1979], n.d. (Box 16)
  - National Association of the Partners of the Alliance 1969, n.d. (Box 16)
  - The National Council for United States-China Trade 1979-1980 (Box 16)
  - Panama Canal Treaties 1977-1978 (Box 16)
  - Panama Canal Treaties 1977-1978 (Box 17)
  - Republican Tax Cut Blitz of New York City 1978 (Box 17)
  - Retirement Speech 1976 (Box 17)
  - South East Asia-Williamsburg Conference 1972, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - U.S.-U.S.S.R. Parliamentary Conference, Moscow 1975 (Box 17)
  - Vancouver, Canada: Williamsburg V Conference 1975, 2 folders (Box 18)
- IV. Photographs
  - Photograph of Secretary of State John F. Dulles and Attorney General Herbert Brownell at the Inauguration of President Eisenhower 1953 (Box 18)
  - Photo of Hugh Scott w/Senator Roman Hruska 1968 May (Box 18)
  - Photo of Apollo 11 Mission w/letter 1969 (Box 18)
  - Photo of Hugh Scott, James Hodgson, and George Tsukahira in Tokyo 1974 Oct. (Box 18)
  - Photo of Hugh Scott and others at the conferences of the American Legion at Korea University 1975 March (Box 18)
  - Photos of Oriental art w/ Arts of Asia magazine 1976 (Box 18)
  - Photograph of Hugh Scott at Wedgwood in London 1977 May (Box 18)
  - Photo of H. S. and others at the Senate Republican Conference 1978 [May] (Box 18)
  - Photo of H. S. at the Youth for Understanding Conference in Tokyo 1978 June (Box 18)
  - Photos of the Youth for Understanding Reception 1981 May 7 (Box 18)
  - Photo of Comparative Studies of the U.S. Congress and the Japanese Diet 1981 (Box 18)
  - Photo of H. S. and others at Youth for Understanding Conference n.d. (Box 18)
- V. Miscellaneous and Printed Material
  - Miscellaneous 1932-1981, n.d. (Box 18)
  - "Let's Stop Picking on the President!", The American Magazine, by Hugh Scott 1953 (Box 18)
  - Program: A Service of Remembrance and Thanks-giving in Honour of Sir Winston Churchill 1965 (Box 18)
  - Program: Dedication of the Old Senate Chamber 1976 (Box 18)
  - Program: The Inaugural Reception in Honor of George Bush, with TLS from Loret M. Ruppe and David R. Scotton 1981 (Box 18)
  - Program: Investiture of Richard Earl Berendzen as Eleventh President of The American University 1981 (Box 18)
  - Program, Magna Carta Ceremony--June, 1976 1976 (Box 18)
  - Record Vote Analysis, 94th Congress, second session: Nos. 1-700 1976, 8 folders (Box 19)
- VI. Memorabilia
  - Certificate of Commendation from Board of Regents of Smithsonian Institution 1976 (Box 19)
  - Retirement: Senate Tributes to Hugh Scott and Related Material 1976 (Box 19)